Stanford University please visit us at stanford.edu thank
you I'm uh honored
to be with you today
for your commencement from one of the
told uh I never graduated
from college and uh this is the closest
I've ever gotten to a college
graduation today I want to tell you
three stories from my life that's
it no big deal just three
stories the first story
is about connecting the dots
I dropped out of Reed College after the
first 6 months but then stayed around
as a drop in for
another 18 months or so before
I really quit
so why' I drop out it started before
I was born
my biological mother was a young
unwed graduate student and she decided
to put me up for
adoption she felt very strongly that
I should be adopted by college graduates
so everything was all set for me to
be adopted at Birth
by a lawyer and a
his wife except that when I popped out
they decided at the last
minute that they really wanted a
girl so
my parents who were on a waiting
list got a call
in the middle of the
night asking we've got an unexpected
baby boy do you
want him they said of
course my biological mother found out
later that my mother had never graduated
from college and that my father had
never graduated from high school
she refused to signed the final adoption
papers she only relented a few months
later when my parents promised that
I would go to college
this was the start in
my life and 17 years later
I did go
to college but I naively chose a college
that was almost as expensive
as Stanford and all of my workingclass
parents savings were being spent on
my college tuition after 6 months
I couldn't see the value in it
I had no idea what
I wanted to do with
my life and no idea how College was
going to help me
figure it out and here
I was spending all the money my parents
had saved their entire life so
I decided to drop out and trust
that it would all work out okay
it was pretty scary
at the time but looking
back it was one of the best decisions
I ever made the minute I dropped out
I could stop taking the required classes that
didn't interest me and begin dropping
in on the ones that looked far more
interesting it wasn't all romantic
I didn't have a dorm room
so I slept
on the floor in friends rooms I returned
Coke bottles for the 5-cent deposits
to buy food with and
I would walk the seven
miles across town every Sunday night
to get one good meal
a week at the Hari
Krishna Temple I loved it and much of
what I stumbled into by following
my curiosity and intuition turned out to
be Priceless later on
let me give you one
example Reed College at that time
offered perhaps the best calligraphy
instruction in the country throughout
the campus every poster every label
on every drawer was beautifully hand
cigraph because I had dropped out
and didn't have to take the normal classes
I decided to take a calligraphy class
to learn how to do this I learned
about serif and Sans serif type faces
about varying the amount of space between
different letter combinations about what makes great typography
great it was beautiful historical
artistically subtle in a way that
science can't capture and I found it
fascinating none of this had even a hope
of any practical application in
my life but 10
years later when we were
designing the first Macintosh computer
it all came back
to me and we designed
it all into the
Mac it was the first
computer with beautiful typography if
I had never never dropped
in on that single course in college the
Mac would have never had multiple type
faces or proportionately spaced fonts
and since Windows just copi the Mac it's
them if
I had never dropped out I would
have never dropped in on that
calligraphy class and personal computers
might not have the wonderful typography
that they do of course it was impossible
to connect the dots looking forward when
I was in college
but it was very very
clear looking backwards 10 years later
again you can't connect the dots looking
forward you can only connect them
looking backwards so you have to trust
that the dots will somehow connect
in your future you have to trust
in something your gut Destiny Life Karma
whatever because believing that the dots
will connect down the road will give you
the confidence to follow your heart even
when it leads you off the well-worn path
path and that will make all the
difference my second story is about love
and loss
I was lucky I found what I love
to do early in life W and
I started Apple
in my parents garage when
I was 20 we
worked hard and in 10 years Apple had
grown from Just the
Two of Us in a
garage into A2 billion doll company with
over 4,000 employees we just released
our finest creation the Macintosh a year
earlier and I just turned
30 and then I got
fired how can you get
fired from a company you
started well as Apple grew we hired
someone who I thought was very talented
to run the company
with me and for the
first year or so things went well but
then our visions of the future began
to diverge and eventually we had a falling
out when we did our board of directors
sided with him and so at 30
I was out
and very publicly out what had been the
focus of
my entire adult life was gone and
it was devastating I really didn't know what
to do for a few months
I felt that I had
let the previous generation of
entrepreneurs down that I had dropped
the Baton as it
was being passed to me
I met with David Packard and Bob noise
and tried to apologize for screwing up so
badly I was a very public failure and
I even thought about running away from the
valley but something slowly began
to dawn on me I still loved what
I did the turn of
events at Apple had not
changed that one bit I'd been rejected
but I was still
in love and so
I decided to start over
I didn't see it then but it turned
out that getting fired from Apple was
the best thing that could have ever
happened to me the heaviness of being
successful was replaced by the lightness
of being a beginner again less sure
about everything it freed me to enter
one of the most creative periods per of
my life during the next 5 years
I started a company named next another
company named Pixar and fell in love
with an amazing woman who would become
my wife Pixar went on to create the
world's first computer animated feature
film Toy Story and is now the most
successful Animation Studio
in the world in
a remarkable turn of events
Apple bought next and I returned
to Apple and the technology we developed it
next is at the heart of Apple's current
Renaissance and L and
I have a wonderful family
together I'm pretty sure none of this
would have happened if I hadn't been
fired from Apple it was awful tasting
medicine but I guess the patient needed
it sometime life sometimes life's going
to hit you in
the head with a brick
don't lose faith I'm convinced that the
only thing that kept me going was that
I loved what I
did you've got to find
what you love and that
is as true for work
as it is for your
lovers your work is going
to fill a large part of your life
and the only way
to be truly satisfied is
to do what you believe is great work
and the only way to
do great work is to love
what you do if
you haven't found it yet
keep looking and don't settle as with
all matters of the heart you'll know
when you find it and like any great
relationship it just gets better
and better as the years roll on
so keep looking don't settle
death when
I was 17 I read a quote that
went something like if you live each day
as if it was your
last someday you'll most certainly
be right it made an impression on me
and since then for the past 33 years
I looked in the mirror every morning
and asked myself if
today were the last day
of my life what
I want to do what I am
about to do today and whenever the
answer has been no for too many days
in a row
I know I need to change
something remembering that I'll be dead
soon is the most important tool
I've ever encountered to
help me make the big
choices in life because almost
everything all external expectations all
Pride all fear of embarrassment or
failure these things just fall away
in the face of death
leaving only what is truly important
remembering that you are going to die is
the best way
I know to avoid the Trap of
thinking you have something to lose you
are already naked there is
no reason not to follow your
heart about a year ago I was diagnosed
with cancer I had a scan at 7:30
in the morning and
it clearly showed a tumor
on my pancreas
I didn't even know what a
pancreas was the doctors told me this
was almost certainly a type of cancer
that is incurable and that I should
expect to live no
longer than 3 to 6
months my doctor advised me to go home
and get my Affairs in order which is
doctor's code for prepare to die it
means to try and tell your kids
everything you thought you'd have the
next 10 years to tell
them in just a few
months it means to make sure everything
is buttoned up so that it will be
as easy as possible for your family it
means to say your goodbyes
I live with that diagnosis all day later
that evening I had a biopsy where
they stuck an endoscope down my throat
through my stomach and into
my intestines put a needle into my pancreas
and got a few cells from the tumor
I was sedated but
my wife who was there told
me that when they viewed the cells under
a microscope the doctor started crying
because it turned out
to be a very rare
form of pancreatic cancer that is
curable with surgery I had the surgery
and thankfully I'm fine
now this was the closest I've been
to facing death and
I hope it's the closest
I get for a few more decades having
lived through it I can now say this
to you with a
bit more certainty than when
death was a useful but purely intellectual
concept no one wants to die even people
who want to go to heaven don't want
to die to get there
and yet death is the
destination we all share no one has ever
escaped it and that is as it should
be because death is very likely the single
best invention of life it's life's
change agent it clears out the old
to make way for the
new right now the new
is you but someday
not too long from now
you will gradually become the old and
be cleared away sorry to be
so dramatic but it's quite
true your time is limited so don't waste
it living someone else's life don't
be trapped by Dogma which is living with
the results of other people's thinking
don't let the noise of others opinions
drown out your own inner voice and most
important have the courage to follow
your heart and intuition they somehow
already know what you truly want
to when
I was young there was an amazing
publication called the whole earth
catalog which was one of the Bibles of
my generation it was created by a fellow
named Stuart brand not far from here
in Meno Park and he
brought it to life with
his poetic touch this was in the late
60s before personal computers
and desktop publishing so it was all made
with typewriters scissors and Polaroid
cameras it was sort of like Google
in paperback form 35 years before Google
came along it was idealistic overflowing
with neat tools and great
Notions Stewart and his team put out
several issues of the whole earth
catalog and then when it had run its
course they put out a final issue
it was the mid 1970s and
I was your
age on the back cover of their final
issue was a photograph of an early
morning Country Road the kind you might
find yourself hitchhiking on if you were so
adventurous beneath it were the words
stay hungry stay foolish it was their
farewell message as they signed off stay
hungry stay foolish and
I have always wished that for
myself and now as you graduate to begin
a new
I wish that for you stay hungry
much the preceding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu